A Guide to the Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9 FA281
Rockefeller Archive Center
Commonwealth Fund records, Child Health Demonstrations, SG 1, Series 9
1921-1928
Rockefeller Archive Center
Harkness, Mary Emma Stillman
Harkness, Charles W.
Commonwealth Fund
Harkness, Anna M. Richardson
Harkness, Edward Stephen
FA281
1.32 Cubic Feet 3 boxes
Conditions Governing Access note
Open for scholarly research, except where particular restrictions are noted.
RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
Biographical/Historical note
The Commonwealth Fund was established in 1918 with an endowment of $10 million from Mrs. Stephen V. Harkness for "benevolent, religious, educational and like purposes." The early grants supported a variety of programs while generally promoting welfare, especially child welfare. Several grants were made in the field of medical research, but the Board of Directors decided in 1920 that this field was already sufficiently supported by other philanthropic organizations.
Despite this decision, by the mid-1920s the chief interest of the Fund had become public health, including mental hygiene, community health, rural hospitals, medical research, and medical education. Other grant areas included war relief, educational and legal research, child welfare, and international medical fellowships.
File Plan note
Former Classification: IX; IV 4B 4
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements note
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be closed to research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be closed to researchers at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/Head of Reference.
Scope and Contents note
The Commonwealth Fund announced its Child Health Program on June 29, 1922. The goals of the five year program were "safe-guarding the health of the mother-to-be, laying a good health foundation for children in the early sensitive and formative period of their growth and health supervision and the formation of the essential health habits in school children." The responsibility for the conduct of the demonstrations rested with the American Child Health Association, which had been recently formed through the merger of the American Child Hygiene Association and the Child Health Organization of America. The Child Health Demonstration Committee of the Commonwealth Fund oversaw the program, with Barry C. Smith chairman and Courtenay Dinwiddie executive director. Other notable participants in the program include Philip Van Ingen, Richard A. Bolt, L. Emmett Holt, Sally Lucas Jean, Livingston Farrand, Donald B. Armstrong, and Barbara S. Quin.
The initial demonstrations were conducted in a city from the Upper Mississippi Valley, the general qualifications being that the population range between 15,000 and 25,000 and the infant mortality rate be approximately 100 per 1000 live births. Twenty-nine cities applied to host the demonstrations, with Fargo, North Dakota, being chosen. The first director of the Fargo demonstrations was Dr. William J. French, former Director of the Child Welfare Commission of Delaware. Subsequent demonstrations were held in Athens (Clarke County), Georgia; Rutherford County, Tennessee; and Marion County, Oregon.
The records of the Child Health Demonstrations consist of the files of the Child Health Demonstration Committee, and the documents relating to the four series of demonstrations. Included are annual reports and research statistics, on-site investigations regarding possible participants, and final report statistics. In the general files are internal memoranda, committee meeting minutes, correspondence, statistical summaries, and weekly reports concerning field observations of the demonstrations.
Other Finding Aids
Other available finding aids describing the Commonwealth Fund records include:
FA247 Commonwealth Fund Harkness House drawings
FA275 Commonwealth Fund records, Advanced Medical Fellowships
FA276 Commonwealth Fund records, Annual Reports
FA277 Commonwealth Fund records, Archives/Library
FA278 Commonwealth Fund records, Austrian Program
FA279 Commonwealth Fund records, Board of Directors
FA280 Commonwealth Fund records, Capital Grants
FA282 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Community Clinics
FA283 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Health Studies
FA284 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Public Health
FA285 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Publications
FA286 Commonwealth Fund records, Division of Rural Hospitals
FA287 Commonwealth Fund records, Educational Research
FA288 Commonwealth Fund records, English Mental Hygiene Program
FA289 Commonwealth Fund records, Finance Committee
FA290 Commonwealth Fund records, Grants
FA291 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Family
FA292 Commonwealth Fund records, Harkness Fellowships
FA293 Commonwealth Fund records, Institute for Child Guidance
FA294 Commonwealth Fund records, Interface Program
FA295 Commonwealth Fund records, Legal Research Program
FA296 Commonwealth Fund records, Living at Home Program
FA297 Commonwealth Fund records, Mental Hygiene Program
FA298 Commonwealth Fund records, Miscellaneous - unprocessed
FA299 Commonwealth Fund records, Personnel - unprocessed
FA300 Commonwealth Fund records, Pilgrim Trust
FA301 Commonwealth Fund records, Program for the Prevention of Delinquency
FA302 Commonwealth Fund records, Reference Files
FA303 Commonwealth Fund records, Reports of the General Director
FA304 Commonwealth Fund records, Treasurer
FA305 Commonwealth Fund records, Turndown Lists - unprocessed
FA306 Commonwealth Fund records, Vertical File (R. Fitz) - unprocessed
FA307 Commonwealth Fund records, Visual Materials
FA389 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Historical Files
FA390 Commonwealth Fund records, Administration - Officers Files
Medicine, Rural; Medical research; Mental health; Medicine -- Scholarships, fellowships, etc.; Child psychology; Child welfare; Education, Rural; Hygiene; Law; Legal issues; Legal research; Medical education; War relief; United States; Public welfare; Public health; New York (State); New York (N.Y.); Child mental health; Social Science Research Council; Harvard University; Columbia University; Yale University; Phillips Exeter Academy
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, December 29, 1921-December 12, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, December 29, 1921-December 12, 1922 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, January 18, 1923-December 27, 1923 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, January 5, 1924-December 29, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, January 5, 1924-December 29, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, January 3, 1925-December 24, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, February 11, 1926-December 27, 1926 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - General Files, January 5, 1927-December 7, 1928 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - Research Unit Report, 1924 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - Research Unit Report, 1925 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - Site Selection Investigations - First Demonstrations, June 1921-November 1922 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - Site Selection Investigations - Southern Demonstrations, March 1923-August 1923 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - Site Selection Investigations - Southern Demonstrations, March 1923-August 1923 (Box 1, Folder 13)
- Child Health Demonstration Committee - Site Selection Investigations - Western Demonstrations, October 1923-November 1923 (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - Annual Report, October 1, 1923-September 15, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 15)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - Annual Report, October 1, 1924-September 30, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - Annual Report, January 1, 1925-December 31, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - Annual Report, January 1, 1926-December 31, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - Annual Report, January 1, 1927-December 31, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - General Files, December 28, 1922-August 16, 1923 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - General Files, May 28, 1924-November 1924 (Box 2, Folder 21)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - General Files, January 6, 1925-November 20, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - General Files, February 22, 1926-December 3, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- Fargo Child Health Demonstrations - General Files, October 2, 1927-April 17, 1928 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1924-December 31, 1924 (Box 2, Folder 25)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1925-December 31, 1925 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1926-December 31, 1926 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1927-December 31, 1927 (Box 2, Folder 28)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Health Education and Physical Education, Dental Service, Sanitation Service, Laboratory Service (Box 2, Folder 29)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Medical Service; Time Distribution and Salary Cost, Health Examinations-Defects and Corrections, Communicable Disease Control (Box 2, Folder 30)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Nursing Services; Time Distribution and Salary Cost, Volume and Intensity of Nursing Visits, School Nursing-Educational and Organizational Activities, Special Studies of Maternity and Morbidity Service (Box 2, Folder 31)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Public Health Expenditures, A.P.H.A. Appraisal Scores (Box 2, Folder 32)
- Athens Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Vital Statistics, Communicable Disease Statistics, Special Studies of Mortality Rates (Box 2, Folder 33)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1924-September 1924 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1925-December 31, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 35)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1926-December 31, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 36)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1927-December 31, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 37)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Community Organization of Rutherford County (Box 3, Folder 38)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Correspondence, November 27, 1923-September 16, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 39)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Correspondence, November 27, 1923-September 16, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Health Education Service, Sanitation Service, Laboratory Service (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Medical Service; Time Distribution and Salary Cost, Health Examinations-Defects and Corrections, Communicable Disease Control (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Nursing Service; Time Distribution and Salary Cost, School Nursing and Organization Activities, Field Visits, Special Study of Maternity Service (Box 3, Folder 43)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Public Health Expenditures, A.P.H.A. Appraisal Scores (Box 3, Folder 44)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Vital Statistics, Communicable Disease Statistics, Special Studies of Mortality Rates (Box 3, Folder 45)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Study of Public Health Activities in Rutherford County, Tennessee, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Survey and Appraisal of the Public Health Activities of Rutherford County, Tennessee, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Rutherford County Tennessee Child Health Demonstration - Survey and Appraisal of the Public Health Activities of Rutherford County, Tennessee, 1923-1928 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1925-December 31, 1925 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1926-December 31, 1926 (Box 3, Folder 50)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1927-December 31, 1927 (Box 3, Folder 51)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Annual Report, January 1, 1928-December 31, 1928 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Health Education Service, Dental Service, Sanitary Service (Box 3, Folder 53)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Medical Service; Time Distribution and Salary Cost, Health Examinations-Defects and Corrections, Communicable Disease Control (Box 3, Folder 54)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Nursing Service; Time Distribution and Salary Cost, School Nursing and Organization Activities, Volume and Intensity of Field Visits, Special Study of Maternity and Morbidity Service (Box 3, Folder 55)
- Marion County Oregon Child Health Demonstration - Final Report - Public Health Expenditures, A.P.H.A. Appraisal Scores (Box 3, Folder 56)